(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-09-02T22:24:55.444548",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
みなさん、こんばんは！ハロー！
Everyone, good evening! Hello!
こんばんは！ハロー！
Good evening! Hello!
ということで、まずは自己紹介からやっていきましょう。
With that, let's start with introductions.
ホロライブの清楚担当、みんなのアイドルの夏色まつりです！
I'm Natsuiro Matsuri, Hololive's seiso representative and everyone's idol!
今日はMCを務めさせていただきます。頑張ります！
I'll be the MC today. I'll do my best!
じゃあ、今日参加してくださる皆さんの自己紹介を
Now, let's have the participants introduce themselves
1人ずついきますよ。
one by one.
じゃあ、よぴぴからお願いします！
Let's start with Yopipi!
はい！イオフォリア・オフィサロ、どうもです。
Yes! Ioforia Ofisaro, hello.
ホロライブインドネシアから、イオフィです！
I am Iofie from Hololive Indonesia!
今日は、オノマトペをちょっと…
Today, I'd like to study a bit
勉強したいと思います。よろしくお願いします！
about onomatopoeia. Please look after me!
お願いします！じゃあ、コボちゃん。
Thank you! Next, Kobo-chan.
わこわこ！わこかなえる！At your service, let me be your sun, shine your day.
Waku waku! Kobo Kanaeru at your service, let me be your sun, shine your day.
こぼ・かなえる、れんしゃ…めーそ
Kobo Kanaeru... [struggling with Japanese]
今日のは、オノマトペは…
Today, for onomatopoeia...
勝ちだ！お願いします！
I'm gonna win! Please look after me!
じゃあ、続いてジジ！
Next up, Gigi!
こんばんは、ジジです。アイム・オニ！
Good evening, I'm Gigi. I'm an Oni!
えーっと、日本語ちょっと上手くない。
Uh, my Japanese isn't very good.
オノマトペ、うーん、ちょっと…
But I'll do my best with onomatopoeia
日本語頑張って、頑張ります！
and Japanese! I'll do my best!
ありがとう！頑張れ！
Thank you! Do your best!
はい、続いて、ほぼJPのべーちゃん。
Yes, next is Bae-chan, who is basically JP.
いやいやいや、ワサワサ！我々はカオス、ハコス・ベールズです。
No, no, no! Waza waza! We are Chaos, Hakos Baelz.
今日は翻訳担当でやりたいと思います。よろしくお願いします！
Today, I'll be acting as the translator. Please look after me!
よろしくお願いします！
Please look after us!
じゃあ、最後は、ラオラ。
Alright, and lastly, Raora.
あっ、こんにちは。ラオラ・パンテーラです。
Ah, hello. I am Raora Panthera.
今日は、えーっと、絵を描いたり、
Today, I'll do my best drawing
日本語で話したり、頑張ります！
and speaking in Japanese!
チャオ！よろしくお願いします！
Ciao! Please look after me!
はい、おねがいします。ということで、本日はですね、
Yes, thank you. So today,
みなさんにオノマトペクイズに答えてもらいます。
we'll have everyone answer an onomatopoeia quiz.
ちょっとね、日本独特の表現とかもたくさんあるんですが、
There are many uniquely Japanese expressions,
頑張って答えてね。
but please do your best to answer!
日本に来るときは、いっぱい使っていただきたいなと思います。
When you come to Japan, I'd love for you to use them a lot!
はい、ということで！
Alright, with that!
早速、第1問、いきましょう。
Let's go straight to the first question!
クエスチョン1！
Question one!
このオノマトペは、何を表しているでしょうか。
What does this onomatopoeia represent?
「コケコッコー」
"Kokekokkoo"
コケコッコー？何これ？
Kokekokkoo? What is this?
Where do you hear this onomatopoeia from?
わからない！
I don't know!
あ、じゃあ、ヒントは、
Ah, then here's a hint.
動物の鳴き声ですね。
It's an animal's cry.
なんの動物の鳴き声でしょう。
What animal's cry is it?
It's an animal cry! What animal makes this sound?
あれ？
Huh?
ちょっと待って、ペンが…
Wait a minute, my pen...
ペンがおかしいんです、私。なんで？
My pen is acting weird. Why?
あ、書けない？
Oh, you can't write?
コケコッコー
Cock-a-doodle-doo.
ケコケコッコッコ
Cack-cack-cackle-cackle.
ペンがおかしい。あれ？なんでこうなっちゃうんだろう？
My pen is weird. Why is it doing this?
ケコケコッコッコ
Cack-cack-cackle-cackle.
書けるかな？
Can I draw?
ちょっと待ってください、アプリ再起動します。すみません。
Please wait a moment, I'll restart the app. Sorry.
Should we draw?
You can do whatever, you can just write it.
I drew it because I don't know what it is in Japanese!
It's alright.
I don't know the word.
何々？あれ？
What is it? Huh?
書けるかな？
Can you write it?
あ、書けます！
Ah, I can write!
あ、よかった。
Oh, good.
よかった。
Good.
終わった。
Finished.
コケコッコー
Cock-a-doodle-doo.
声に出したらわかるかも。
If you say it out loud, you might understand.
コケコッコー
Cock-a-doodle-doo.
鳥？
Bird?
大丈夫かい？
Are you okay?
コケコッコー、コケコッコーでしたよ。
It was cock-a-doodle-doo.
コケコ！
Cackle!
おー。OK、じゃあ、一人ずつ聞いていきましょう。じゃあ、よぴぴ、何だと思いますか？
Oh. Okay, then, let's ask one by one. So, Yopipi, what do you think it is?
あ、チキンです！
Ah, chicken!
お、チキン！はいはいはい。
Oh, chicken! I see, I see.
にわとりね、はい。
A rooster, right.
はい、じゃあ、コボちゃん。
Yes, next, Kobo-chan.
Ah, before I was thinking about frog, but I think "koke-kokko" is...
It sounds like Indonesian "kukuruyuk"!
So, it's chicken!
おお！なるほど！
Oh! I see!
なるほどね。
I see.
なんか、元々カエルだと思ってたんだけど、なんかインドネシアのオノマトペでも…
She thought it was a frog at first, but in the Indonesian onomatopoeia...
オノマトペに、なんかニワトリの音に似てるので、チキン。なるほど。
...it sounds like a rooster, so chicken. I see.
はい、じゃあ、ジジ。
Yes, next, Gigi.
えー、ケコケコッコッコ、英語は... Cock-a-doodle-doo! Chicken.
Well, cackle cackle cackle, in English it's... Cock-a-doodle-doo! Chicken.
同じだね、チキン。じゃあ、べっちゃん。
The same, chicken. Then, Bae-chan.
あ、僕もニワトリ、チキン。だと思います。
Ah, me too, rooster, chicken. I think so.
はい、じゃあ最後はラオラ。
Yes, and finally, Raora.
Ah... for me it's like a bird that is screaming like "koko",
...like "I'm here!" and...
あ、ココ？
Oh, "here"?
He wants food in his mouth because maybe he is small, you know, I don't know.
Bae-chan, what do you think it is? A bird?
Bird? Sakebutori.
鳥、叫ぶ鳥ね。
A bird, a screaming bird, right.
お腹空いている叫ぶ鳥ね。
A hungry screaming bird, right.
了解。
Roger.
じゃあ、正解いきましょう。正解は...
Then, let's see the correct answer. The correct answer is...
チキン！ニワトリでした！
Chicken! It was a rooster!
You got it! Yay!
まあ、正解にしますか。叫ぶ鳥だもね。
Well, should we count it as correct? It is a screaming bird.
叫ぶ鳥は鳥。鳥は鳥、同じだからね。素晴らしい。
A screaming bird is a bird. A bird is a bird, it's the same. Wonderful.
Everybody gets a point! Yay!
コケコッコー、コケコッコーでした。
Cock-a-doodle-doo, it was cock-a-doodle-doo.
はい、じゃあ続いて、第２問。
Yes, now for the second question.
こちらも動物の鳴き声でございます。
This is also an animal sound.
Oh, the second question is also the sound of an animal.
はい、第２問はこちら。ケロケロ。
Yes, the second question is this: Kero-kero (ribbit ribbit).
あ、ケロケロ！
Oh, kero-kero!
Easy! Easy!
ケロケロ。
Ribbit ribbit.
書けるかな？
Can you draw it?
べっちゃん、それは… え？
Bae-chan, that is... What?
ええ？すごい！
Huh? Amazing!
何？何？何？何？
What? What? What? What?
Eh, my pen... Okay, it works.
ケロケロ、ケロケロ、ケロケロ…
Ribbit ribbit, ribbit ribbit...
ケロケロ。かわいい、ケロケロ。
Ribbit ribbit. Cute, ribbit ribbit.
ラオラ、大丈夫？
Raora, are you okay?
Oh, yes, okay. Okay, it's working. Thank you.
べっちゃんの何？
What is Bae-chan's?
え？
What?
Wait, hold on, I forgot what it looks like!
Is that an owl?
What are you drawing?
Why is she drawing herself?
I forgot what it looks like!
べっちゃんの…
Bae-chan's...
It looks like a chimera, you know. Chimera-like.
きめるわ
I'm locking it in!
Oh my god! きめるのやめて
Oh my god! Don't lock it in!
おっしゃ、ちょっと1人ずつまた聞いていきますか？
かわいいみんな。
Alright, let's ask everyone one by one.
You all drew so cutely.
えー、じゃあ、よっぴぴ！
Let's start with Yoppipi!
あい！カエル、Frogです。
Yes! It's "kaeru", a frog.
あ、Frog。ケロケロ。でしょ？
Oh, frog. Ribbit-ribbit. Right?
うんうん、なるほど。あい！
Right, right. I see. Yes!
じゃあ続いて、コボちゃん！
Next up is Kobo-chan!
私もカエル！カエル、はい。
ケロケロ、ケロケロ。
Me too, a frog! A frog, yes.
Ribbit-ribbit, ribbit-ribbit.
ケロケロ。
Ribbit-ribbit.
すごーい！
Awesome!
まつりも書けないの？カエル。
Matsuri, can't you write "kaeru" either?
はい、続いて、ジジ！
Alright, next up, Gigi!
はい！ケロケロ、ケロッピー！
Yes! Ribbit-ribbit, Keroppi!
あ、ケロケロケロッピー？おー！
Ah, Kero Kero Keroppi? Oh!
なるほど。じゃあ、べーちゃん！
I see. Next, Bae-chan!
あ、カエルです。
Ah, it's a frog.
お？カエルかな？
Oh? Is it a frog?
カエルです。
It's a frog.
カエーーール！カエーーール！
Frog! Frog!
一瞬ネズミに見えたんだけど。
For a second, it looked like a mouse to me.
確かにね、カエル見たことないんで。
True, since I've never seen a frog.
一応カエル。カエル。カエルが白枠。
But it's supposed to be a frog.
A frog. In the white frame.
その隣の、ラオラ、めっちゃ絵うまい。かわいい！
Next to her, Raora,
you're so good at drawing. Cute!
かわいい！
So cute!
カエルですね？
It's a frog, right?
うん。カエルです。
Yeah, it's a frog.
はい。じゃあケロケロ、正解は？
Alright, so "kero kero"...
the correct answer is...
カエル！でございます。正解！
Frog! That is correct!
ナイスナイス！イージー、イージー。
Nice, nice! Easy, easy.
簡単だった！
That was easy!
日本語上手、日本語上手よ。ねー。
Your Japanese is so good. So good. Right?
じゃあ続いて行きますよ。続いては、こちら！
Let's move on to the next one. The next is this!
馬の鳴き声は？日本だと何と言うでしょうか？
"What sound does a horse make?"
What do we call it in Japan?
Oh, what sound does a horse make?
Japanese onomatopoeia.
わからない！なんて聞こえるかな？
I don't know! What does it sound like?
なんて聞こえるかな？
What does it sound like?
うー。
Hmm...
お耳。
The ears.
イメージ、イメージして。
Imagine it, visualize it.
It's alright, Gigi. Feel it from your heart.
You can do it!
1人ずつ鳴いてもらうからね。
I'm going to have you make the sound one by one.
She's going to ask each of you to sound out the onomatopoeia that you have come up with.
オッケー？オッケーオッケー。
Okay? Okay, okay.
じゃあ、1人ずつ鳴いてもらいますか。
Well then, let's hear everyone's horse sounds.
よっぴぴから。よっぴぴの馬の鳴き声、
お願いします。どうぞ。
Starting with Yoppipi. Yoppipi's horse sound,
please. Go ahead.
はりきっていこう！
Let's do our best!
え、それ？はりきっていこう？
Eh, that? "Let's do our best"?
それ違うでしょ。
That's not it.
そうやって鳴く...
Is that how they...
馬、これしか知らないですよ！
I only know this horse pun!
じゃあ続いて、コボちゃん！
Next up, Kobo-chan!
ひひー！ひひー！
Hi-hee! Hi-hee!
おお！ひひー！ひひー！
Oh! Hi-hee! Hi-hee!
I feel like that's a different sound.
ひひー！ひひー！
Hi-hee! Hi-hee!
じゃあ続いて、ジジ！
Next up, Gigi!
えー、えー...
Uh, uh...
ブルルル！ブルルル！
Prrr! Prrr!
ワイルドホース！
Wild horse!
じゃあ続いて、べーちゃん！
Next up, Bae-chan!
えーっと...
Let me see...
ウマ！ウマ！
Horse! Horse!
めっちゃ日本語喋るやん。
You're speaking straight Japanese.
じゃあ続いて、ラオラ！
Next up, Raora!
オッケー。えー、 maybe something like...
Okay. Uh, maybe something like...
ヒヒーン！
Neigh!
リアル！リアル！
So realistic! So realistic!
Wow! You are a cat,
but your voice sounds like a horse.
めっちゃ似てた。
That was a perfect imitation.
正解は、馬の鳴き声って何？
So, what actually is the Japanese horse sound?
「ヒヒーン」でした。
It was "hihiin"!
ヒヒーン？ヒヒーン？
Hihiin? Hihiin?
1番惜しかったのはラオラじゃないの？
Wasn't Raora the closest?
ラオラはリアルすぎたかな？
リアル、リアル。
Maybe Raora was too realistic?
Realistic, realistic.
ヒヒーン。
Hihiin.
Oh, there is an "n" at the end.
ヒ・ヒ・ン。ヒヒーン。
Hi-hi-n. Hihiin.
Why do horses make that sound?
Sound like Michael Jackson.
Sounds like Michael Jackson.
ヒヒーン。
Hihiin.
私 2点？ Am I count?
My 2 points? Am I counted?
Oh, yeah, Kobo does!
Ah, hihu. I have hihu too!
No hihu. No hihu?
No hihu, no.
No hihu?
So it's not counting?
So it's not counted?
Not counted.
No count, sorry.
No hihu hihu.
Hihu. Hihu.
はい。残念ながら不正解でございます。
Yes. Unfortunately, that is incorrect.
では、続いて、えー、今から言う言葉の意味を当ててください。
Moving on, please guess the meaning of the phrase I'm about to say.
意味を当ててください。じゃあ、いきます。
Please guess the meaning. Here we go.
What is the meaning of this?
「ぺこぺこだー！」の意味。
The meaning of "Peko-peko da!"
あ、はいはいはいはい！
Ah, yes, yes, yes, yes!
What does peko-peko mean?
おー。みんな、スラスラと書いてくれている。
Oh, everyone is writing it down so smoothly.
ぺこぺこ、ぺこ。
Peko-peko, peko.
「ぺこぺこだ！」 ぺこぺこだー！
"Peko-peko da!" "Peko-peko da!"
ぺこぺこだー！
"Peko-peko da!"
オッケーかな？オッケーかな？
Are we okay? Are we okay?
可愛いイラストが書かれている。
Some cute illustrations are being drawn.
じゃあ、聞いていきますか。
Well, shall we hear your answers?
じゃ、ヨピっぺ！
First, Yopippe!
はい！Hungryです！食べたいです！プリン食べたいです！
Yes! It's "hungry"! I want to eat! I want to eat pudding!
食べたい、Hungry。
"Want to eat," hungry.
食べたい。
I want to eat.
オッケー。ペコペコです。ペコペコ。
Okay. Peko-peko. Peko-peko.
じゃ、コボちゃん！
Next, Kobo-chan!
はい！ぺこぺこ、インドネシア語の意味は、laperです。
Yes! "Peko-peko" in Indonesian means "laper."
laperとはどういう意味？
What does "laper" mean?
Laperはhungry！
"Laper" is hungry!
あ、hungry！あー、hungry！hungry！
Ah, hungry! Oh, hungry! Hungry!
Hungryね。オッケー。
Hungry, okay.
じゃ、ジジ！ジジ、顔しか書いてないけど。
Next, Gigi! Gigi, you only drew a face.
お腹空いた！ぺこぺこ！
I'm hungry! Peko-peko!
お腹空いたね。オッケー、オッケー。可愛い。
Hungry. Okay, okay. Cute.
じゃ、続いて、ちちゃん！
Next, Ceci-chan!
はい、Hungryです。あれ？腹減った。
Yes, it's "hungry." Ah? "Harahetta."
腹減った、オッケー。
"Harahetta," okay.
じゃあ、らおら！
Then, Raora!
あ、very hungry！
Ah, very hungry!
おー。じゃ、全員同じだね。全員hungry。
Oh, so everyone is the same. Everyone is hungry.
Hungry, hungry!
はい、ということで、全員正解！
Yes, so with that, everyone is correct!
イェーイ！Easy, easy, easy! 上手上手！
Yay! Easy, easy, easy! Good job!
はい、じゃあ続いて、また当ててください、意味を当ててくださいね。
Yes, next, please guess again. Guess the meaning.
Next one is also guess the meaning!
「チンしてね！」の意味は？
What is the meaning of "Chin shite ne!"?
Huh? Oh!
「チンしてね！」
"Chin shite ne!"
チンしてね！チンしてね！
"Chin shite ne!" "Chin shite ne!"
チンしてね。チンしてね。
"Chin shite ne." "Chin shite ne."
チンしてね？！
"Chin shite ne"?!
チンしてね。
"Chin shite ne."
チン。わかるかな？声に出したらわかるかもよ？チン。
"Chin." Do you get it? Maybe if you say it out loud? "Chin."
Pee please? Pee please?!
はい、じゃあ聞きますか。
Yes, well, shall we hear your answers?
えー、ヨピっぺ、どうでしょう？
So, Yopippe, how about you?
はい。最初はちょっと、ドアのベルだったんだけど、あれピンポンだから、チンしたらマイクロウェーブ？
Yes. At first, I thought it was a doorbell, but that's "pin-pon". So "chin" is... microwave?
あ、マイクロウェーブ。うんうん。
Ah, microwave. Yes, yes.
あの、温める？終わったらチンって鳴るじゃん。
Like, heating it up? When it finishes, it goes "chin", right?
うんうん。なるほど。
Yes, yes. I see.
はい。じゃあ、コボちゃんは？
Okay. Then, Kobo-chan?
あれ？あれ？
Wait? Wait?
コボちゃん？コボちゃん？これは？
Kobo-chan? Kobo-chan? What is this?
なんか、チンは...
Well, "chin" is...
ちょ、ちょ！いやいやいやいや！
Wait, wait! No, no, no, no!
コボちゃん？！
Kobo-chan?!
そういう意味？！そういうものみたい？！
That's what you think it means?! It sounds like that?!
その「チン」は、おしっこの「ちん」...
That "chin" is like "chin" for pee...
チン、プリーズ？！「チン、プリーズ」って？！
"Chin, please"?! What is "chin, please"?!
たぶん、わからない。
Maybe... I don't know.
わからない？わからない。
You don't know? I don't know.
なるほど。じゃあ次行きますか。じぃじぃ、おねがい。
I see. Let's move on to the next person. Zeta, please.
I わからない。
I don't know.
ち、血やばい...
My... my blood is in trouble.
血やばい？！やばいやばい！血がやばい！
Blood in trouble?! Oh my god! Blood?!
脳やばい？脳やばい！
Brain in trouble? Brain is in trouble!
それやばくない？もう。
Isn't that bad? Seriously.
じゃあ、べーちゃん、べーちゃんお願いします。
Okay, Bae-chan, Bae-chan, please.
はい。レンジのチンですね？
Yes. It's the microwave's "ping", right?
あ、温めて...っていうことで。
As in, warming it up...
Please go warm it up in the microwave.
うん。はいはいはい。じゃあ最後、ら、らおら！
Yes, yes, yes. Then last, Raora!
えー、わからない。わからない。
Uh... I don't know. I don't know.
わからない？
You don't know?
Maybe...
Maybe something like...
Maybe when the glass, when it touch the glass?
Maybe when the glass... when it touches the glass?
ガラス？おお、ガラスね！
Glass? Oh, glass!
ガラスね。はいはい。ちーんって言うから？確かに！
Glass, right. Yes. Because it clinks? True!
Not yabai.
Not crazy.
Not yabaiね。Not yabai。Not yabai。
"Not crazy," indeed. Not crazy.
もうわかんないよ。はい、わかんない。
I have no idea. Yes, no idea.
じゃあ、こちらはですね、正解は...Microwave！ちん！
Okay, the correct answer for this is... microwave! Ping!
ああ、なるほど。
Oh, I see.
ご飯を温めてください、っていう...
Like, "Please warm up the food..."
When you want to warm up food in a microwave, you say 'chin'.
チンしてね。
"Chin shite ne."
チンしてね。あ、なるほど。
"Chin shite ne." Ah, I see.
例えば、ご飯をこう、置いといて、
For example, leaving the food out...
あとに帰ってきた人、ご飯が冷めちゃってるから
...for someone who comes home late, since the food gets cold,
「チンしてね」って、メモをね、残したりしますね。
...you might leave a note saying, "Chin shite ne" (please microwave it).
なるほど。なるほど。
I see. I see.
コボ、コボ、チンしてね。チン、チン。
Kobo, Kobo, microwave it. Microwave, microwave.
Like, 'please warm it up for me.' Chin shite ne.
Oh, okay. So, if you wanna say 'pee, please'...
Oh, okay. So, if you want to say "pee, please"...
はい。Yeah, how do you say that? I might need that one.
Yes. Yeah, how do you say that? I might need that one.
No pee!
No, no pee!
じゃあ、peeはどう言ったらいいの？
Then, how do you say "pee"?
Peeってあれ、pee please... Onomatopoeia, pee please.
"Pee" is like, "pee please"... Onomatopoeia, "pee please."
Pee pleaseって何？
What is "pee please"?
おしっこ？
Pee?
おしっこ。おしっこ。
Pee. Pee.
ああ、じゃあ、し、シー、シャーとか。
Oh, then, "shii" or "shaa" maybe.
シャー。シャー、please！
"Shaa." "Shaa, please!"
シャー、please！シャー、please、なるほど。
"Shaa, please!" "Shaa, please," I see.
はい、シャーとか、シーとか。
Yes, like "shaa" or "shii."
シャー、おねがい。
"Shaa, please."
No, no, no, no, no! No, ダメよ。
No, no, no, no, no! No, don't say that.
すみません、シャーおねがい。
Excuse me, "shaa" please.
ダメ、ダメ、ダメ！
No, no, no!
おしっこ、ありがとうございます。わかりました。
I got the word for "pee", thank you. I understand.
やべぇ。えー、じゃあ、ネクストいきましょう。
Oh my god. Okay, let's go to the next one.
こちらでございます。
Here it is.
静まり返ったとき、めっちゃ静かなとき使うオノマトペは何でしょうか。
What is the onomatopoeia used when a room goes completely silent?
What's the onomatopoeia that they use when it goes really quiet?
Oh, maybe I remember.
え？
Eh?
静かなとき。
When it's quiet.
What that mean?
What does that mean?
What? Really, really quiet.
静かなときも音があるんですよね。
Even when it's quiet, there's a sound effect.
Like, when it goes really quiet all of a sudden, what's the onomatopoeia that they would use?
You can write it in romaji, or you can just sound it out.
I'm going to write the onomatopoeia I just learned.
すー？
"Suu"?
漫画を読んでたらわかるかもね。漫画に書いてある、あることもあるかも。
If you read manga, you might know it. It's often written in manga.
Japanese manga.
In Japanese manga.
Might be in manga that you've read before.
Oh, what is it? Like that?
Is that how you say?
I don't know how to spell it.
まあまあ、いいでしょう。なになになに。
Well, well, that's fine. What is that?
じゃあ、聞いていきますね、よぴぴから。
Okay, let's hear the answers, starting with Kaela.
はい。しーん。
Yes. "Shiin."
はい、しーん。多分、こうやってしーん。
Yes, "shiin." It's written like "shiin."
じゃあ、続いて、こぼちゃん。
Next, Kobo-chan.
しーー！
"Shiii!"
うん、うん、うん。しー。しー。はいはい。
Yes, yes, yes. "Shii." "Shii." Okay.
じゃあ、じぃじぃ。
Okay, Zeta.
シャー！
"Shaa!"
シャー？！シャー！シャー！
"Shaa?!" "Shaa!" "Shaa!"
シャー。
"Shaa."
Isn't that the pee? No!
Wait, we're gonna get quiet after you pee?
The quiet after you pee!
おおー、では続いてべちゃん！
Oh, next is Bae-chan!
いや、そ、忘れた、なんか、すん...
No, I... I forgot. Like, "sun"...
あ、すん！
Ah, "sun"!
違う、すんはちょっと違うか。
No, "sun" is a bit different.
しーになったか。
So it was "shii"?
え、どっちかと思ってたんだよね。なるほど。
Well, I thought it was one of them. I see.
じゃあ、続いてらら！
うーん...
Now, next is Raora!
Hmm...
お、しーん？
うん、yes!
Oh, "shiin"?
Yes, yes!
Yeah, I think it's "shiin".
Like, I remember when I read some mangas... I might be wrong...
Maybe it's "shiin".
うんうん、しーん、おーけー。マンガにね、おーけー、got it.
Yeah, yeah, "shiin", okay. In manga, okay, got it.
おっけー。じゃあ正解いきましょう。
Okay. Let's see the correct answer.
正解は、しーーん！でございます。
The correct answer is... "Shiiin"!
やっぱり！やったー！
I knew it! Yay!
ららちゃんが正解だね！
Raora got it right!
You were so close, Gigi. You're so close.
Gigiのは、しー、しーん。
そう、しー。
Gigi's was "shii", "shiin".
Yeah, "shii".
「ん」が必要ですね、コボちゃん。「し」、「ん」...
You needed the "n" sound, Kobo-chan. "Shi" and then "n"...
おしい！Close!
So close! Very close.
Very close.
じじは絶対違うからね。
Gigi's is definitely wrong, though.
シャーー！
Shaaa!
シャーーってw
"Shaaa" lol
さっきのピーの音...
The pee sound from earlier...
でも、一応なんか理屈的にも間違ってないと思うんですけどね。
But logically speaking, I think she's not wrong.
え？
Eh?
じじがさ、おしっこした後にさ、静かになるじゃん？
You know, after Gigi pees, it gets quiet, right?
そうそうそう、さっき言ってた...
Yeah, yeah, what we were saying earlier...
だからシャーー！
シャーーw ちょっと違うw
So, "Shaaa"!
"Shaaa" lol. That's different!
I was explaining your logic.
Oh, okay, thank you. So you're defending me?
Yeah, I was defending you.
I got you, I got you.
はい、じゃあ続いていきましょう。
Yes, let's move on.
続いて、「とっても冷たい飲み物」を表すオノマトペは何でしょうか？
Next, what is the onomatopoeia for an "extremely cold drink"?
Oh, what's the sound of an extremely cold drink?
飲み物...
そう、冷たい...
A drink...
Yes, a cold...
あれと、あれだけど...
It's either this or that, but...
何々に冷えた、って言いますね。
あれでしょ？
We say, "Chilled to..." something.
It's that, right?
うーん...
Hmm...
Cold drink... I only have one word in my head again!
Do my eyes deceive me?
Cold drink...
Cold drink.
うーーん...
Hmm...
これもね、マンガに出てくるかもね。
Maybe manga, aha.
This might also appear in manga.
うーーん... わかんない！
Hmm... I don't know!
Image... image...
What sound? If I get it wrong, oh my...
What do you have, Raora? Just do it! Just do it!
I'm scared!
No! It's okay!
No!
じじがなんかヤバそうだ。
Gigi looks like she's in trouble.
何を書こうとしてるの、じじ大丈夫？
What are you trying to write? Gigi, are you okay?
じじ大丈夫？大丈夫？
Gigi, are you okay? Are you okay?
大丈夫、大丈夫。
大丈夫。
She's okay, she's okay.
I'm okay.
大丈夫、はいはい。
Okay, yes, yes.
でも、あれかな、ビールとかに結構言うかな？
But, maybe it's used a lot with beer?
Ah, used with beer? Hmm.
おっけー。じゃあ、いきましょうか。じゃあ、よっぴぴ！
Okay. Let's hear the answers. Next is Yo-pipi!
はい！
Yes!
たしか、キンキンなんとかのうにゃららです。はい。
I think it's "kinkin" something something. Yes.
えっと、なんかこの前スタジオで、ホロメンの誰かさんがマネージャーに「キンキンな飲み物ほしいです」って言われた。
Um, the other day at the studio, one of the Holomems told their manager, "I want a kinkin cold drink."
おおー！なるほど！
Oh! I see!
そうそうそう、去年の夏ぐらいに。誰かさん、ちょっと忘れちゃったんだけど、スタジオでなんか聞いたことがある。
Yeah, yeah, around last summer. I forgot who it was, but I heard it at the studio.
おー、キンキンね。おっけー。じゃあコボ。
Oh, kinkin. Okay. Next is Kobo.
Ah, so, I thought like, when you... after you drink cold, a really cold drink...
...your head will hurt and then you will say, "Atata!"
冷たいもの飲んだ後さ、頭痛くなるじゃないですか？
After drinking something cold, your head hurts, right?
その時に「あたたたたた！」って。
At that time, you go "atata-tata"!
だからこその「あたたた」って回答しました。
That's why she answered "atata".
おっけー、おっけー。はい、じゃあ続いて、じじ。
Okay, okay. Yes, then next, Gigi.
Hmm, eh...
さむい！
Cold!
さむいw Yes!
Cold lol.
Yes!
さむい？さむい、うまい？
Cold? Cold, delicious?
さむい、うまい。さむいうまいw
Cold, delicious. Cold-delicious lol.
かわいい。
Cute.
おっけー。「さむい」。さむい飲み物、おっけー。
Okay. "Cold". Cold drink, okay.
はい。
Yes.
はい、オッケー。可愛い！
Yes, okay. So cute!
じゃ、続いてはベちゃん。
Next up is Bae-chan.
なんか「き」から始まった気がした。あ、忘れた。
I feel like it started with "Ki". Oh, I forgot.
「き」から始まる。きー、なんか、きー。
It starts with "Ki". "Ki..." Something like "Ki..."
きー、きー、きー。
Ki, ki, ki...
きー、オッケー、オッケー。きー。
Ki... Okay, okay, okay. "Ki."
じゃ、ラオラ。
Now, Raora.
あー、えー、It's a かんぱい！
Ah, er... It's "Kanpai!" (Cheers!)
あ、乾杯！乾杯！
Ah, cheers! Cheers!
かんぱい、Let's go. オッケー。
Cheers! Let's go! Okay.
乾杯！
Cheers!
じゃ、正解行きましょう。正解は、
Now, let's reveal the correct answer. The answer is...
「キンキンに冷えた飲み物」でございますので、
"A ice-cold, chilled drink."
キンキンですね。
So the word is "Kin-kin" (ice-cold).
キンキン！キンキン！キンキンってすごい！
Kin-kin! Kin-kin! That's amazing!
ユタ、ありがとう！誰かさんのホロペン、ありがとうございます。
Yuta, thank you! Thank you, someone's HoloPen.
キンキンか。
So it was "Kin-kin."
「キンキンに冷えてやがるよ」っていうセリフがアニメにもありますね。
There's an anime line like, "It's ice-cold!"
ほうほうほう。
Oh, I see.
はい。
Yes.
じゃ、続いては、えーと、行きますか。続いてはこちら。
Now, let's move on to the next one. Here it is.
きらきら。「星がきらきらしてる」みたいな、きらきらのもっと強い表現。
"Kira-kira." An even stronger expression for sparkling, like twinkling stars.
もっときらきら。
Even more sparkly.
もっと眩しい？お？ほうほうほう。どう表現するでしょうか？
Even more dazzling? Oh? I see. How would you express that?
So how would you describe something that, you know, you have "kira-kira" to describe something that's sparkling,
something that's even more bright and shiny?
More? More than "kira-kira"?
これじゃないの？
Is it not this?
あ、これは結構何パターンかある。
Ah, there are actually a few different patterns for this.
There's a couple of different variations.
あれ？なんとかの、ほにゃららの、えーと、ポケモン思い出っちゃって。
Wait... some kind of... I just remembered a Pokémon.
ポケモン。
Pokémon?
Like Pokémon?
えー？
Eh?
So, so like "kira-kira", but...
but stronger, yeah, like... with more punch.
Level up kira-kira.
Level up kira-kira. Powerful kira-kira.
きらきら？
Sparkling?
きらきら。
Kira-kira.
きらきら。わかるかな？
Kira-kira. Do you get it?
可愛い。
Cute.
I'm bribing the judge.
What? I'm bribing the judge.
Why? She's bribing... she's trying to bribe the judge.
Why bribing the judge? Why?
I don't know the word.
なんか、MCさんに賄賂してます。
She's bribing the MC.
何？何？
What? What?
あの、知らないので、あの、MCに賄賂してます。
Um, since I don't know it, I'm bribing the MC.
賄賂？はい。あー、そういうこと？
A bribe? Yes. Ah, is that what it is?
じゃ、ヒントね、ヒント。
Then, here's a hint. A hint.
ヒントは、えー、ホロライブメンバーの曲の歌詞に入ってますね。
The hint is... it's in the lyrics of a Hololive member's song.
Oh, it's in the lyrics of a Hololive member's song!
もっと言うと、ねねちの。
To be more specific, Nenechi's.
ねねちのあの曲。In Nenechi's song? に、入ってる。
That song of Nenechi's. "In Nenechi's song?" Yes, it's in it.
あとは、きらきらの進化。きらきらパワーアップさせた感じかな？
Also, the evolution of "kira-kira." Like a powered-up version of it.
おお！がヒント。どうでしょうか？わかるかな？
"Oh!" is the hint. How about that? Do you get it?
オッケー、賄賂オッケー。おお。
Okay, bribe accepted. Oh!
賄賂は、え、これ賄賂くれるの誰？誰がくれたの？
Speaking of the bribe, wait, who gave me this bribe? Who was it?
ジジ？ラオラ？ジジかな？
Gigi? Raora? Maybe Gigi?
ジジ？ジジ。
Gigi? Gigi.
あ、ジジじゃあ、賄賂として、あの、
Ah, then Gigi, as a bribe,
Very cute voice, please, Matsuri-oneesan, okay?
頼む。あの、あの映画の賄賂な感じを。
I beg you. Like that bribing scene in that movie.
あ、そういう？
Oh, like that?
えー、きらきら、えー、まつりおねえさん、きらきら！
Uh... Sparkly, uh... Matsuri-oneesan, sparkly!
大好き！
I love you!
ぐあー！
Gwah!
き、きしょ...やば！可愛い！
That was... wait, gross... Oh my god, so cute!
あ、ジジ、あの、your name word, hint. Your name word.
Ah, Gigi, um, your name is a word... hint. Your name word.
Your name is a hint? My name is a hint? It is.
オッケー？あ、あれね！
Okay? Ah, that one!
で、えー、ま、ねねちの曲にも入ってるよと。
And, well, it's also in Nenechi's song.
オッケー。
Okay.
いけるかな？ じゃあ聞いてこ。
Ready? Let's hear your answers.
じゃあ、よぴから。
Let's start with Yopi.
はい、えっと、基本漢字キラキラとかのそういうの、
Yes, um, basically I thought it was "kirakira"...
かな、と思ってて。
...or something like that.
でも今思ってたら、あれだなと思ってて。
But now that I think about it, I'm not so sure.
お。変えますか？
Oh, do you want to change it?
あ、いや、大丈夫です！でもなんか
Ah, no, I'm fine! But somehow,
そう、なんか、そのキラキラより強いのが、なんか
yeah, something stronger than "kirakira", like...
いつも太陽、太陽がピカッ、ピカッってなるじゃないですか。
the sun, the sun is always shining bright, isn't it?
太陽によく使われるものかな。
I think it's something often used for the sun.
なるほど、はいはいはいはい。
I see, yes, yes, yes.
じゃあ、ベイビーちゃん。
Okay, Bae-chan.
ええっと。
Well...
Cause I heard someone saying...
Uh, uh, Pokemon?
So, ahaha.
So I think, like...
Pika Pika!
ピカピカ！
Pikapika!
ピカピカ、なるほど、オッケー。
Pikapika, I see, okay.
確かに強い。確かに強い、ピカピカ。
That's definitely strong. Pikapika is strong, indeed.
Strong, strong pikapika!
じゃあ、続いてジジ！
Next is Gigi!
ええー。
Well...
ギラギラ！ギラギラ！
Giragira! Giragira!
はん、はい、ギラギラ、オッケー？
Aha, yes, giragira, okay?
オッケーオッケー。じゃあ、エリーちゃんいきましょう。
Okay, okay. Let's go with Ellie-chan.
あ、僕もピカピカだと思った。
Ah, I also thought it was pikapika.
ピカピカね、オッケー。
Pikapika, okay.
えー、じゃあラオラ。
Okay, then Raora.
Ah, same for me. I heard about Pokemon...
...so I thought about Pikapika, too.
おお、ポケモンヒントからね。なるほどなるほど。
Oh, from the Pokemon hint. I see, I see.
オッケー。じゃあ、正解いきましょう。
Okay. Let's look at the correct answer.
正解は...
The correct answer is...
ギラギラ！で、ジジ正解！
Giragira! Gigi is correct!
ギラギラ！
Giragira!
天才じゃん！
I'm a genius!
天才、天才、天才！
Genius, genius, genius!
買収されたわ。買収された。
I was bribed. I was bribed.
ギラギラ。
Giragira.
ピカピカ、ちょっと惜しくて、それがね、ビカビカとかだったら正解。
Pikapika was close. If it had been "bikabika", that would be correct.
ああ、ビカビカ！ もっと眩しい。
Oh, "bikabika"! It's even brighter.
ああ、ビカビカの方が強いんだ。
Ah, "bikabika" is stronger.
そう。ピカピカはまあ、キラキラと同じくらいしか。
Yes. "Pikapika" is only about the same as "kirakira".
同じ？ なるほど。
The same? I see.
ちょっと弱いかな。ビカビカ、ギラギラ。
It's a bit weaker. "Bikabika", "giragira".
Pika pika is on the same level as kira kira.
Pikapika is on the same level as kirakira.
そっか。いつも聴いてるのが、なんか「ギラギラ太陽なんとか」っていう。
I see. I always hear things like "glaring sun something-or-other" in songs.
あ、そうそうそう。
Ah, yes, yes, yes.
ねねちゃんのね、あのギラファもね、ギラギラ。
Nene-chan's "Giraffa" is also "giragira".
ギラファとかもね。
Like "Giraffa" and stuff.
と同じ感じで、明るい眩しいみたいな、ことだと思いますね。
It has the same feel, meaning bright and dazzling.
I see, I see. The more you know.
Bribing works! Bribing works? I mean, I could bribe!
Yeah, bribing works! Okay, nice, nice, nice.
続いていきましょう。続いて、同じ感じでございますけども
Let's move on. Next is the same kind of question...
心臓のこの音、「どきどき」をもっと強く表現すると？
How do you express this heartbeat sound, "dokidoki", more strongly?
Stronger "dokidoki"?
Bigger than "dokidoki"?
どき... あれ？
Doki... Huh?
これもね、何パターンかあるから、合ってたら大丈夫です。
There are several patterns for this too, so if you get any of them, it's fine.
何パターンあるんだ。 どちらでもいい、って感じですか、そしたら。
How many patterns are there? So any of them is fine? Trumpet?
まあ、2つ3つくらい表現はあるかな。
Well, there are about two or three expressions.
どきどき... うん。
Dokidoki... Yeah.
どきどきね。どきどき、どきどき。
Dokidoki. Dokidoki, dokidoki.
どきどき、どきどき。
Dokidoki, dokidoki.
もっと強く、強く。強く？ うん。
More strongly, more strongly. Strongly? Yes.
どきどきが...
"Dokidoki" becomes...
ちなみに、弱くすると...
By the way, if you make it weaker...
まあ、弱くすると、とくん、とくん、とかですね。
Well, if you make it weaker, it's "tokun, tokun".
おお、お、オッケー。 これもちょっとヒントになるかな。
Oh, okay. Maybe this is a little hint.
とくん、とくん、どきどき。
"Tokun tokun", "dokidoki".
Another, like, similar level is "tokun tokun", so that's a hint.
So you want something stronger than "tokun tokun".
おお、なるほど。
Oh, I see.
あ、これもちょっと何か、可愛い声で、まつり先輩、あ、まつりお姉さんって言ったら、ヒントくれます？
Ah, can you give us another hint if we ask "Matsuri-senpai... I mean, Matsuri-oneesan" in a cute voice?
ヒント？！
A hint?!
ヒント、ヒント欲しいですか？
Do you want a hint?
かわいく、まつりお姉さんって言ったら、ヒントあげます。
If you say "Matsuri-oneesan" cutely, I'll give you a hint.
あ、オッケー。オッケー。
Ah, okay, okay.
いいよ、どうぞ。
Sure, go ahead.
え、え、いいんですか？
Wh-What? Really?
いいよ。
Go ahead.
え、いいんですか？ まつりおね...
Really? Matsuri-onee...
お姉ちゃん、ちょっと、あの、ヒントお願いします。
Sister, please give us a hint.
しょうがないにゃあ。
I guess I have no choice.
1つだけでいいから、お姉ちゃん！
Just one hint is fine, sister!
Oh my god.
めっちゃこれヒントだけど、あの、まあ、強調するのに、日本では結構小さい「っ」を入れたりとか。
This is a huge hint, but to emphasize it in Japanese, we often insert a small "tsu"...
あ、あ！なるほどです！
Ah, ah! I see!
あとは、言葉を変えるんだったら、あの、なんだろう、大きな音っぽいというか。まあ「どっ」もね、大きそうだけどね。
Also, if you were to change the word, it's like a bigger sound... well, "do" already sounds big, though.
はい。そんな感じですかね。
Yes, something like that.
はい！ありがとう、お姉ちゃん！
Yes! Thank you, sister!
うお、うお。よし。
Whoa, whoa. Alright.
Okay, okay. Yeah, yeah, you could totally bribe the MC.
Why did you guys bribe the MC?!
じゃあ、えー、よーぴ、じゃ、行きますか？
Then, shall we go with Yo-pi first?
はい！「どっくん」です！
Yes! It's "dokkun"!
はい、どっくん。どっくん、どっくん。
Yes, "dokkun". "Dokkun, dokkun".
はい、どうぞ。じゃあ、コボ。
Okay, please go. Next, Kobo.
Ah, I remembered to mock Zeta about a part of her original song lyrics. It's "babu-babu", but it's actually "bagu-bagu" or "bagu-bagu". Yeah, something like that.
あー、ばぐばぐ。
Ah, bagu-bagu.
じゃあ、続いて、じーじ。
Then, next is Gigi.
はい、ウマ娘。どき、どきどき。どっきゅん！どっきゅん！
Yes, Umamusume. Doki, dokidoki. Dokkyun! Dokkyun!
あー！どっきゅんどっきゅん！
Ah! Dokkyun dokkyun!
はい！/ はい、はい、はい。なるほど。確かに。
Yes! / Yes, yes, yes. I see. Indeed.
じゃあ、べーちゃん。
Then, Bae-chan.
いや、もうドキドキをもっと強くして、もはや心臓破送。
Well, making "doki doki" even stronger, to the point of heart explosion.
ドドドドドドドド！
Dododododododo!
はい。
Yes.
じゃあ、ラオラ。
Then, Raora.
えっと、ばっくんばっくん！
Um, bakkun bakkun!
あー、ばっくんばっくん。
Ah, bakkun bakkun.
I was listening recently, so... yeah. That must be it.
これね、全員正解でいいかなと、思います！
Everyone's is quite different, but the correct... the winner is...
For this, I think everyone can be correct!
Oh, everyone's right?! Awesome!
結構いろんな表現があって、
There are quite a few different expressions,
まあ、「どっきん」とか「どっくん、どっくん」とか、「どきどき」、「どっきどき」とか。
like "dokkin", "dokkun dokkun", "doki doki", "dokki doki".
あと「ドドドドド」も強そう。
And "dododododo" also sounds strong.
ドドドドドは死んでるよ！
Dododododo means you're dead!
死んでる！
Dead!
緊張してるときとかに、「ドドドドド」って心臓の音を表現したりとか。
Like when you're super nervous, you express the heartbeat as "dododododo" sometimes.
はい、ということで全員正解！素晴らしい！
Yes, so everyone is correct! Wonderful!
じゃあ、ちょっと、今度は、
Well then, next,
今度は、今からとあるサウンドを聞いてもらいます。
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
Next, you're going to listen to a certain sound.
あ、チャンネルにボイスを貼りますので、聞く。
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
Ah, I'll post the voice clip in the channel, so listen to it.
これ何て言っているでしょうか？という問題でございますね。
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
The question is: what is it saying?
何を言っている？
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
What is it saying?
今から蝉の鳴き声を送ります。何て言っているでしょうか、蝉は。
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
I'm going to send a cicada's chirp now. What is the cicada saying?
All right, she's sent a little voice clip. What is this cicada saying in the voice clip?
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
じゃあ、リスナーさんにも聴かせます。こちらです。
Then, I'll let the viewers hear it too. Here it is.
Oh, so we have to come up with the onomatopoeia. Okay. From listening to it... It's in the chat.
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
はい、これは何と聞こえる... / なるほど、なるほど。
Yes, what does this sound like...? / I see, I see.
So what is that sound that the cicada is making?
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
日本人だったらね、絶対にわかるね。
If you're Japanese, you'll definitely know.
So, how do you pronounce it? Cicada? Is it cicada?
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
Cicada, cicada... I always pronounced it like "chichada"!
Chichada? Enchilada!
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
I thought it was chichada!
これは何かな？ / What does it look like? Cicada? Cicada.
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
What is this, I wonder? / What does it look like? Cicada? Cicada.
It has big wings. Yeah.
（画面表示：このセミ鳴き声は？）
見たことない。
I've never seen it before.
I've seen it all the time inside here.
本当に？
Really?
They're everywhere.
Everywhere.
これは勝ったら...
If we win this...
JPやね。
...JP wins, right?
さすがに。
As expected.
セミ...
Cicada...
本物の...
A real...
お、セミ見たことないんです。
Oh, I've never seen a cicada.
え？！
What?!
え？いないの？
Eh? Are there none?
いや、いるとは思うんだけど、声は聞こえるけど、姿がなんかどこにいるのかわかんない。
No, I think they're around, and I can hear them, but I don't know where they are, like their physical appearance.
そうんだ。え、子供の頃セミ捕りとかしないの？
Oh, I see. Did you not catch cicadas when you were kids?
ない。
No.
あれは多分、結構なんか日本文化的な...
That's probably a very Japanese cultural thing...
ああ、へー！そうなんだ！
Ah, I see!
ないない。
No, we don't.
じゃあ、セミの種類とか言われてもあんまわかんないのか。
So if we talk about cicada species, you don't really know them?
わかんない！全部セミだもん！
We don't! They're all just cicadas!
確かに。
True.
そうなんだ。
Is that so?
Anyone of you guys caught cicadas before? Caught us...
Have any of you guys caught cicadas before?
Cicada? Ever caught one before?
No.
I got one in my balcony.
I got one on my balcony.
え？
Eh?
Your balcony?
On your balcony?
Yeah.
Balcony?!
It was huge! It was like super big!
And it was super loud!
バルコニーに？
On the balcony?
ベランダ、ベランダね。
Veranda, veranda.
ベランダにいた？
It was on the veranda?
そんなに大きいの？
Was it that big?
セミって。
A cicada?
結構デカいよ。よくいるよ、その辺で死んでるのとか。
They're pretty big. You often see dead ones lying around.
マジ？！
Seriously?!
Big bug.
コボは大丈夫とかな？
I wonder if Kobo is okay with them?
大丈夫くない。
I'm not okay.
大丈夫くない！何回も聞いていいよ。
She's not okay! You can listen to it again.
大丈夫じゃない？
You're not okay?
何回も。大丈夫ない。
Again. I'm not okay.
Can I have a hint?
ヒント！ヒントお願い！
Hint! Hint please!
ヒントは、なんかあの「ショワショワショワ」って言ってるのは無視していい。
The hint is, you can ignore the "showa showa showa" sound.
その、大きい低めの音のセミさんはなんて言ってるかだね。
Listen to what the loud, lower-pitched cicada is saying.
おお。
Oh.
Focus on the lower sounding notes, ignore the "showa showa" in the background.
困ってるね。
We're in trouble.
オッケー。
Okay.
オッケー、じゃあ行きましょう。よぴぴから。
Okay, let's go. Starting with Yopipi.
はい。みー、みー...
Yes. "Mee, mee..."
はいはい、みーみーみーみー、はい。
Yes, yes. "Mee, mee, mee, mee," yes.
みーね、オッケー。
"Mee," okay.
じゃあ、コボちゃん。
Then, Kobo-chan.
ちー...
Chee...
かわいい。
Cute.
ちー、ちー。
"Chee, chee."
ちーだね、かわいい。
It's "chee." Cute.
はい、じゃあジジ。
Okay, next is Jiji.
ジジは、じーじーじーじーじー...
Jiji is "jee-jee-jee-jee-jee..."
ジジの鳴き声！
Jiji's call!
おお。
Oh.
じゃあ、続いてべちゃ。
Then, next is Becha.
え、
Uh...
うぃーー！
Wryyyy!
うぃー、オッケーオッケー。
"Wryy," okay, okay.
じゃあ、ラスト、ラナ。
Then, last is Rana.
あ、えーと、くり、くり、くり、くり...
Ah, um, "kuri, kuri, kuri, kuri..."
あ、かわいい、「くりくり」。
Ah, cute, "kuri-kuri."
オッケーオッケー。
Okay, okay.
じゃあ、正解いきましょう。正解は、
Now, let's see the correct answer. The correct answer is...
はい。
Yes.
みーーんみんみんみんで、よぴぴ正解！
"Mee-ee-n min min min," Yopipi is correct!
やった！
Yay!
It doesn't sound like "min min" at all.
聞こえないんだよね、M。Mの音なくない？
You can't hear the "M," right? Isn't there no "M" sound?
There is no M sound.
このセミの名前がそもそも「ミンミンゼミ」という名前のセミね。
The name of this cicada is originally "Minmin-zemi."
あ、ミンミンゼミ。
Ah, Minmin-zemi.
「みーんみんみんみん」って日本人には聞こえてます。
It sounds like "mee-n min min min" to Japanese people.
へー。
I see.
じゃあ、続いてネクストセミいきますよ。
Now, moving on to the next cicada.
ネクストセミ？
Next cicada?
One more セミいきます。
Let's do one more cicada.
One more セミ？
One more cicada?
セミ2、こちらです。じゃあ、皆さんにも聞かせます。
Cicada 2 is this one. Let's let everyone hear it.
はい。セミ2。
Yes. Cicada 2.
What is this?
なにこれ？！
What is this?!
What is this sound from?
I don't know.
What the heck?!
Haha, what the...
セミバージョン2ですよ。
This is cicada version 2.
What is this?
わかるかな？セミ2ね。
Do you know it? Cicada 2.
ヒントお願いします！
Hint, please!
ヒント！
Hint!
ヒントは...
The hint is...
What is...
ヒントは？
What's the hint?
あの、タタタタターン、タタタタターンっていうのが、鳴き声。
Well, the call goes "ta-ta-ta-ta-taan, ta-ta-ta-ta-taan".
タタタタターン？
Ta-ta-ta-ta-taan?
タタタタターン。
Ta-ta-ta-ta-taan.
が、日本人には、タ・タ・タ・タ・タン、だからまあ、5文字くらいかな？
To Japanese people, it's "ta-ta-ta-ta-tan", so maybe about 5 characters?
え？5？
Huh? Five?
Can you focus on the sound that makes that pattern?
うーん、パターン？
Hmm, pattern?
ヒント難しいね、これは。
Giving hints is hard for this one.
ヒントとして難しいな。
As a hint, it's hard.
その、タタタタターンもオノマトペだと言われたら、もうごめんなさい、それは...
If you say "ta-ta-ta-ta-taan" is also onomatopoeia, then I'm sorry, that is...
えー？ むず...
Huh? Hard...
もうダダダダダしか聞こえへん。
I can only hear "da-da-da-da-da".
うーん、意味...
Hmm, the meaning...
You got this, guys. We got this.
まあ、伸ばし棒が入ります、あと、最後の方に。
Well, there is a macron (elongated vowel) at the end.
え？
Eh?
There is an elongated... there is an elongated sound?
伸ばすと7文字ですね。
If you include the elongated sound, it's 7 characters.
ええ？
Eee?
ちょっと、諦め用に流しとくか。
Maybe I should play it again to help you give up.
難しいね。
It's difficult.
This is, this voice...
リズム、実体は分かるんだけど、どう書いていいか分からない。
I can understand the rhythm itself, but I don't know how to write it.
落ち着く。
Calming.
ね。
Yeah.
この、この声を聞くと落ち着きますよ。夏だなって。
If you hear this voice, you feel calm. Like, "Ah, it's summer."
ええ？
Eee?
How is this sound relaxing to Japanese people?
ええ？
What?
ええ？落ち着くよね？
Huh? It's calming, right?
Okay.
じゃあ、いきましょうか。よぴぴから。
Then, let's go. Starting with Yopipi.
いや、ク・ク・ク・ク・クじゃないですか？セミ バージョン２。
No, isn't it ku-ku-ku-ku-ku? Cicada version 2.
セミ バージョン２？
Cicada version 2?
セミ、ク・ク・ク・ク、オッケー？
Cicada, ku-ku-ku-ku, okay?
オッケー、オッケー。じゃあ、じーちゃん。
Okay, okay. Then, Gigi-chan.
Um... so...
The previous one was min-min, right?
うん。アハ。
Yeah. Aha.
And, uh, I heard this is more than min-min, so it's a mating call like 'mang mang, mang mang!'
ちょっと待って。
Wait a minute.
そもそも, why did you write 'mating call'?
First of all, why did you write "mating call"?
えーと、求愛の鳴き声。ミンミンです。
Uh, mating call. It's min-min.
あ、でも求愛の鳴き声なんだよね、実際。
Ah, but actually, it is a mating call.
あ、そうなの？
Oh, really?
そう、そう。Yes.
Yes, yes. Yes.
Wait, so it is a mating call! It's a mating call!
Oh my god!
セミのオスが、あの、メス来て！って言ってる時の声だから、そこは正しい。
It's the sound of a male cicada saying "Hey, females, come here!", so that part is correct.
ええー！ Oh my god, oh my god!
Eee! Oh my god, oh my god!
It is?
でも、でも、ミンミンが正しいかどうかね。
But, but, whether "min-min" is correct or not...
あっ、そう、ミンミンね、オッケー。
Ah, right, min-min, okay.
Whether it's min-min or not.
オッケー、ということで。チチ。
Okay, so. CC.
Um, tsuku-tsuku-g, tsuku-tsuku-g, tsuku-tsuku-g...
オッケー、ツクツクGオッケーね。
Okay, tsuku-tsuku-G is okay.
じゃあ、べちゃん。
Then, Be-chan.
え？なんか... puku-puku-puku-puka! Puku-puku-puku-puka!
Eh? Like... puku-puku-puku-puka! Puku-puku-puku-puka!
ポケモンっぽかったんだけど。
That sounded like a Pokemon.
ポケモン... puku-puku, puku, puku-puku-puka.
Pokemon... puku-puku, puku, puku-puku-puka.
オッケー。
Okay.
じゃあ、ラオーラ。
Then, Raora.
In my opinion, it's a cricket, and the cricket sounds like 'pring pring, pring pring!'
ぷりんぷりん、可愛い。
Pring pring, cute.
Pring pring, pring pring.
But it's a cricket!
For you.
じゃあ、いきます。こちらの鳴き声は...
Okay, here we go. This call is...
ツクツクボウシでございます！
Tsukutsukuboushi!
えええー！
Eeee!
何、何で？何で？何で？Why?
What, why? Why? Why? Why?
ツクツクボウシ、ツクツクボウシ、ツクツクボウシ、ツクツクボウシ！
Tsukutsukuboushi, tsukutsukuboushi, tsukutsukuboushi, tsukutsukuboushi!
So I should do this if I want to mating call someone?
ツクツクボウシ！ Not tsuku-tsuku-G?
Tsukutsukuboushi! Not tsuku-tsuku-G?
Not tsuku-tsuku-G, 求愛の鳴き声。
Not tsuku-tsuku-G, it's a mating call.
Tsukutsukuboushi! Sha-please! Sha-please!
Tsukutsukuboushi! Shut up, please! Shut up, please!
まあ、ツクツクボウシか、ツクツクホウシ、どっちでもオッケー。
Well, tsukutsukuboushi or tsukutsukuhoushi, either is okay.
ツクツクホウシ？どっちでもオッケーです。
Tsukutsukuhoushi? Either is okay.
ツクツクホウシ、ツクツクホウシ... となっております。はい。
Tsukutsukuhoushi, tsukutsukuhoushi... That's what it is. Yes.
ちょっとね、これセミは難しいですね。
Yeah, cicadas are difficult.
セミの種類とかは関係ないんですか？
Does the species of cicada not matter?
あ、これはツクツクボウシっていうセミの鳴き声ですね、今のは。
Ah, this is the call of the cicada species called "Tsukutsukuboushi", the one just now.
あ、種類？そう、種類もツクツクボウシっていう名前のセミ。
Ah, species? Yes, the species itself is also a cicada named "Tsukutsukuboushi".
ちなみに他にも、さっきのがミンミンゼミだったでしょ？アブラゼミっていうのが、あの、ジジがさっき言ってた、ジジジジジジジって泣くのがアブラ...
By the way, the previous one was Minminzemi, right? Aburazemi is the one that goes "ji-ji-ji-ji-ji-ji" like Gigi was saying...
セミだったり
...like a cicada...
アブラゼミ
Aburazemi.
はい。
Yes.
日本人だったらセミの声を聞くだけで何のセミかわかります。
If you're Japanese, just by hearing a cicada's call, you can tell what kind of cicada it is.
えー！
Eh?!
Wow! Wow!
They can differentiate what kind of cicada it is depending on what it sounds like.
There's different enchiladas?
Enchila- Yeah, so what we heard were two different enchiladas, Gigi.
So you're saying that there is an enchilada that says Gigi?
Yes, there is.
え、3種類って何の名前だったっけ？
Wait, what were the names of those three kinds again?
えーと、ジー・ジー・ジーはアブラゼミですね。
Well, "ji-ji-ji" is the aburazemi, right?
アブラゼミ！
Aburazemi!
アブラゼミ。Yes, aburazemi.
Aburazemi. Yes, aburazemi.
A large brown cicada.
Large brown cicada, gosh.
なるほど。なるほど。
I see. I see.
続いてラスト問題！
Next up, the final question!
ラスト！これはめっちゃちょっとジャパニーズすぎる。難しいと思うんですけど、
The last one! This is a bit too Japanese-specific, so I think it'll be difficult...
これ解けたら、いつ日本に来ても戦えます。
But if you can solve this, you can fight whenever you come to Japan.
戦える？Okay.
Fight? Okay.
日本には独特な、これにしか使わないオノマトペがあります。
In Japan, there is a unique onomatopoeia used only for this.
桃が川から流れてくるオノマトペは何でしょう？
What is the onomatopoeia for a peach floating down a river?
Honestly, an onomatopoeia for when a peach comes floating down the river?
Momotaro!
桃太郎呼んでないんだったら、これ...
If you're not calling Momotaro, then...
呼んでないんだったら、できないじゃないですかこれ、桃太郎。
If you aren't calling Momotaro, you can't solve this.
これわかったら...
If you know this...
What is the sound that a peach makes when it flows down the river? It's a very, very specific onomatopoeia.
I'm guessing if you know the story of Momotaro...
Is it folklore?
Yeah, you know Momotaro? The Peach Boy? Yes.
Oh my god, it's very specific.
これ、桃にしか使わないですね。リンゴとかが代わりに流れてきても、使わない。
This is only used for peaches. Even if an apple floats down instead, we don't use it.
Eh?! Only used for peaches? It's only peaches. Gosh.
I'm sure this is gonna be really weird.
Momotaro, I read it once.
Oh, then you should know.
Maybe I know it, then, but... oh, because I've watched...
If you read the actual book, it's written in the actual book. Like in Japanese.
So if you haven't read it, then you probably don't know.
I don't know...
なんか確かに前に、あの、雑談配信でこれのことちょっと語った気がする。
Actually, I think I talked about this a bit during a chatting stream before.
あ、そうなんだ！
Oh, really!
そう。でもなんでこうなったのって言われたらわかんない。
Yeah. But if you ask me why it became like that, I don't know.
すごいね、でも。話すんだ、昔話ね。
That's amazing, though. You talk about folk tales.
はい。
Yes.
What was it...
これはね、多分知らないと本当に当てられないと思うけど。
If you don't know this, I think you really won't be able to guess it.
日本人だったら、あの、ちっちゃい子から、おじいちゃんおばあちゃんまで、みんなわかるからね。
But if you're Japanese, from small children to grandpas and grandmas, everyone knows it.
桃の川流れてる音、なんだって。
Like, what is the sound of a peach floating down a river?
はい、じゃあ行きましょうか、最終問題。じゃあ、よぴぴ、どうでしょう？
Alright, let's go! The final question. So, Yopipi, how about you?
はい、どんぶらっこです。
Yes, it is "donburako".
はい、どんぶらっこ、どんぶらっこ。オッケー。
Yes, donburako, donburako. Okay.
じゃあ、こぼちゃん。
Now, Kobo-chan.
モンゴモンゴ。
Mongo-mongo.
モンゴモンゴ！かわいい。
Mongo-mongo! Cute.
おしりみたい。
It looks like a butt.
流れてるの。
Floating down.
うん、おしりみたい。
Yeah, like a butt.
じゃあ、ジジ。
Now, Gigi.
Um, if I saw a huge peach floating in the water, and it was like a really big peach and it was huge, and it was, you know, like a peach,
I would go, "Ah, wow, dekai!"
Mecha mecha juicy, dekai!
Very, very juicy, dekai (huge)!
Juicy, dekai!
でかいって言っちゃう？
She'd say "it's huge"?
Osiri dekai!
Osiri dekai! (Big butt)
おしりでかい！
Osiri dekai!
Oh my.
はい、じゃあベちゃん。
Okay, next, Bae-chan.
Well, like, "donpisha"!
Donpisha.
水の音、じゃあ...
The sound of water, then...
Donbisha.
はい。
Yes.
じゃあ続いて、ラオラ。
Okay, next, Raora.
Uh, maybe it's "puka puka".
Ah, puka puka!
Puka puka, cute!
オッケー、じゃあ正解いきましょう。正解...
Okay, let's see the correct answer. The answer is...
うわ！
Whoa!
どんぶらこ、どんぶらこ...
Donburako, donburako...
どんぶらこ、どんぶらこですね。
Donburako, donburako.
なぜです？
Why is that?
なぜかは そうやって本に書いてあるからね。
Why? Because that's how it's written in the book.
理由は無い。
There's no reason.
え、ちなみに...
By the way...
理由は無い？
No reason?
ない、ない。
No, none.
It's because it's written like that in the book.
うん、そう。
Yeah, exactly.
で、あれだね。「ぷかぷか」は、
So, that. "Puka puka" is...
浮いてるもの、水に浮いてたら「ぷかぷか」で合ってる。
...for floating things. If it floats on water, "puka puka" is correct.
Oh, so if it's floating in the water, it would be puka puka.
But because it's coming down the stream,
it's flowing down the stream...
...どんぶらこ、どんぶらこ。
...it's "donburako, donburako."
そう、桃が川から流れてくるときは「どんぶらこ」ですね。
Yes, when a peach flows down a river, it's "donburako."
And it has to be a peach?
If it's an apple or anything else, it's not...?
りんごだったら何？
What if it's an apple?
りんごだったら「ぷかぷか」。
If it's an apple, it's "puka puka."
Oh my god.
桃だけ。
Only peaches.
Peach only? "Donburako"?
Peach only.
ということでね、えー皆さん。
So, everyone...
Why, Japan?
難しいよね、オノマトペ。
Onomatopoeia is hard, isn't it?
でも、可愛かったのでね。
But since it was cute...
あ、で、ちなみにオノマトペでは無いんですけど、
Ah, and by the way, this isn't onomatopoeia,
今日みんなに覚えていってほしい言葉があります。
but there is a word I want you all to learn today.
全然わからない、
"I don't understand at all"...
全然わからないっていうのを、日本語では「ちんぷんかんぷん」と言いますね。
...to say "I don't understand at all" in Japanese, we say "chimpun kampun."
あー！ちんぷんかんぷん！
Ah! Chimpun kampun!
かわいい。
So cute.
ちんぷんかんぷん。
Chimpun kampun.
ちんぷんかんぷん！
Chimpun kampun!
ちんぷんかんぷん。そうそうそう。
Chimpun kampun. Yes, yes, yes.
ちんぷんかんぷん。
Chimpun kampun.
これは「全然わからない」。
This means "I don't understand at all."
When you have no idea of anything, this is the onomatopoeia you use?
When you have no idea of anything, this is the word you use?
ちんぷんかんぷん。
Chimpun kampun.
I like that, I like that.
I'm very scared of you using this phrase, GG.
Every time someone asks me something, "chimpun kampun."
I'm just scared of you forgetting what the full phrase is.
ちん...
Chin...
ちんから始まった言葉ですよ、ちんぷんかんぷん。
It's a word that starts with "chin," "chimpun kampun."
はい、ということで。
Yes, so...
怖いな、ちんぷんかんぷんっていう言葉を、
I'm a bit scared she might forget the "chimpun kampun" word...
全部覚えられない時があったら...
...and if she can't remember all of it...
「ちん」って。
...she might just say "chin."
忘れたら「ちん」ね。
If you forget, just "chin."
覚えられない事実が怖いんだよ。
The fact that she might not remember is what's scary!
覚えて、「ちんぷんかんぷん」。漢字もあるからね、ちんぷんかんぷんって。
Remember, "chimpun kampun." There are kanji for "chimpun kampun" too.
え、漢字もあるの？
Eh, there are kanji?
そう、漢字もあります。
Yes, there are kanji.
カタカナじゃなくて？
Not in katakana?
カタカナで書いたりひらがなで書くことが多いけど、ちゃんと漢字がある。
It's often written in katakana or hiragana, but there are proper kanji.
漢字が？
Kanji?
そう。
Yes.
漢字があるんだ。
There are kanji for it.
はい。
Yes.
読めない、難しそう。コメントで書いてくれている。
I can't read it, looks hard. People are writing it in the chat.
それが「ちんぷんかんぷん」ですね。
That is "chimpun kampun."
珍しい...
"Rare..."
珍しい粉？漢字の「珍」「糞」「漢」「糞」...
Rare powder? The kanji "珍" (rare), "糞" (dung), "漢" (man), "糞" (dung)...
ちんぷんかんぷん。
Chimpun kampun.
でも、めっちゃ可愛いから、もし日本語わかんなくなったら
But it's really cute, so if you don't understand Japanese,
「日本語ちんぷんかんぷんです」って言ったら、もうオッケー。
you can just say "My Japanese is chimpun kampun," and it's all good.
全て解決。
That solves everything.
オッケー。
Okay.
オッケー、わかった。
Okay, got it.
There is one onomatopoeia that Okayu senpai taught me once.
おお！おかゆ先輩が教えてくれたオノマトペ。
Oh! An onomatopoeia Okayu-senpai taught you.
何ですか？
What is it?
"Burun burun" desu.
It's "burun burun."
ぶるんぶるん？「ぶるんぶるん」は...
Burun burun? "Burun burun" is...
おっぱいを、おっぱいを揺らす時の音。
The sound of shaking, shaking boobs.
Oh my!
ぶるんぶるん。
Burun burun.
え、ぶるんぶるん？
Eh, burun burun?
「ぼいんぼいん」じゃないの？
Isn't it "boin boin"?
「ぼいんぼいん」も合ってる。
"Boin boin" is also correct.
ぼいんぼいん、ぶるんぶるん、オッケー。どっちもおっぱい。
"Boin boin" and "burun burun" are both okay. They both refer to boobs.
で、もっと大きなおっぱいだと「ばいんばいん」になります。
And if they are even bigger, they become "bain bain."
ばいんばいん。もっと！もっと大きなおっぱいは「ばいんばいん」。
Bain bain. Even! Even bigger boobs are "bain bain."
ばいんばいん。
Bain bain.
それ以上大きなぶるぶるはないですか？
Are there no jiggly sounds bigger than that?
それ以上大きいのはないね。「ばいんばいん」が一番大きい。
There's nothing bigger than that. "Bain bain" is the biggest.
なるほど。
I see.
ということで。
So...
今日の優勝者、一応発表しますか？
Shall we announce today's winner?
今日はですね、よっぴぴが優勝でございます。
Today's winner is Yoppipi!
あ、やったー！
Oh, yay!
すごい！
Amazing!
半分以上正解して。
You got more than half correct.
やった！
Yay!
天才。さすが。
Genius. As expected.
さすがでございます。
As expected indeed.
いやいやいや、日本語上手だから。日本語上手。
No, no, no, my Japanese is just good.
でもね、他のメンバーもあれですよ。半分は正解してますから。
But you know, other members also got at least half correct.
素晴らしいでございます。
So everyone did wonderfully.
おおー！やったー！
Oh! Yay!
ということで、皆さん本日もありがとうございました。
And with that, thank you everyone for watching today.
チャンネル登録もね...
Also, please subscribe...
ありがとう！ありがとう！
Thank you! Thank you so much!
サンキュー！じゃ、チャンネル登録も...あ。
Thank you! So, please subscribe... Ah!
チャンネル登録の方も...
Please subscribe...
ぽちっとお願いしますね。
...with a simple click!
お願いします！ / ぽちっ！
Please! / Click!
お願いします！
Please do!
ということで、じゃ、最後はバイバイで終わっていきますよ。せーの！
And with that, let's finish with a goodbye. Ready, go!
バイバーイ！サンキュー！
Bye-bye! Thank you!
ちーぽんぽん！ちーぽんぽん！ちーぽんぽん！
Chi-pon-pon! Chi-pon-pon! Chi-pon-pon!
ぶるんぶるん！バイバイ！バイバイ！
Broom-broom! Bye-bye! Bye-bye!